Guide to the Charles Lawrence Bristol Papers MC.47
New York University Archives
Charles Lawrence Bristol Papers
1881-1908, 1930
New York University Archives
Bristol, Charles Lawrence, 1859-
MC.47
0.25 Linear Feet in 1 half manuscript box.
This collection contains material spanning from 1881 to 1935, relating to Charles Lawrence Bristol's time as both a student and professor of biology at New York University. Bristol graduated from NYU and later served as a professor at the University Heights campus from 1894 to 1925. He was named professor emeritus in 1926, a position he held till his death in 1931. This collection contains articles, a pamphlet, a notebook, and correspondence written by Bristol.
Biographical Note
Charles Lawrence Bristol was a professor of biology at New York University from 1894 to 1931. Bristol was the son of Lawrence W. Bristol and Caroline (Hawkins) Bristol, born in Ballston Spa, NY, on September 29, 1859. He married Ellen Sands Gallup on January 28, 1890.
He received both his Bachelor of Science (1883) and Master of Science (1888) degrees from University of the City of New York (later NYU). During his undergraduate career at the University, he served as Junior Orator, Commencement Orator, Vice President, Secretary, and Treasurer and Librarian of the Eucleian Society. He received the First Butler Eucleian Essay Prize in 1882.
Bristol began teaching in the biology department at NYU's University Heights campus in 1894. In 1926 he was awarded the position of professor emeritus of biology, a position he held until his death in 1931. Bristol taught an array of courses such as human anatomy and physiology, general biology, comparative anatomy, and vertebrate zoology.
Scope and Contents
This collection in its entirety spans from 1881-1930. The bulk of the collection consists of scientific articles written by Bristol relating to his scientific research in biology, marine biology and geology, including a biological research station that he founded in Bermuda. These materials range in publication date from 1881-1908. This collection also includes a notebook written by Bristol during his time as a student on geology lectures delivered by Dr. John J. Stevenson during the spring term of 1883. Correspondence from 1930 relating to the sale and transfer of a slide collection owned by Bristol can also be found in the collection.
Arrangement
The collection has been organized into three series. Folders are arranged chronologically.
Series I. Articles and Pamphlet Written by Charles Bristol, 1881-1908
Series II. Notebook, 1883
Series III. Correspondence, 1930.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The provenance for this collection is unknown. There is no accession number associated with this collection.
Biology.; Stevenson, John J. (John James), 1841-1924; New York University. Faculty of Arts and Science; New York University -- Students
- Series I: Articles and Pamphlet Written by Charles Bristol, 1881-1908
  - "Entomology: Is it a hobby or not?" The University Quarterly, Volume IV, May 1881 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "With Edison," The University Quarterly, Volume VI, pp. 51-56, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The New York Aquarium," Popular Science Monthly, Volume LVII, No. 4, pp. 405-412, February 1901, Febraury 1901 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Notes on the Bermudas," reprinted from Bulletin of the American Geographical Society, June 1901 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "The Bermuda Biological Station for Research" [pamphlet], March 1905 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Some Principles Underlying Breeding," printed in Connecticut Farmer, New Haven, Volume XXXVII, No. 33, August 15, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Notebook, 1883
  - Notes on Geology from lectures on the same delivered during Spring term (January to March 1883) by Professor John J. Stevenson before the senior class at NYU, January-March 1883 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Series III: Correspondence, 1930
  - Correspondence regarding sale of slide collection, January 1930 (Box 1, Folder 8)